{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This man built a gigantic bridge over the Bay of Baiae to prove to a soothsayer he could ride a horse over the bay. This man’s predecssor was smothered by the Praetorian Prefect Macro. This emperor ordered an invasion of Britain that ended with his men collecting sea shells instead. Suetonius claimed that this man planned to make his horse Incitatus consul. The nickname “Little Soldier’s Boot” was given to, for ten points, what insane Roman emperor?",
      "answer": [
        "Caligula",
        "Gaius Caesar",
        "Gaius Julius Caesar Augustus Germanicus",
        "do not"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "One of these phenomena, nicknamed the “mud-eater” for its effects on Provence’s agriculture, is known as the mistral. William of Orange’s invasion of England was enabled by a so-called “Protestant” version of this phenomenon, which also destroyed Philip II’s Armada, preventing a Spanish takeover. The Portuguese used the term “volto de mar” to describe their caravels being powered by, for ten points, what meteorological phenomenon that powers sailing ships?",
      "answer": [
        "winds",
        "close equivalents like storm, but not “rain”",
        "mistral before mentioned",
        "Protestant wind after “William” is mentioned",
        "tradewinds after “volto” is mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In this war, a group of German mercenaries under French leadership called Lauzun’s Legion saw action at White Plains. A German officer in this war ordered the establishment of separate toilets and kitchens and educated troops about marching orders during a brutal winter encampment. A group of Hessian soldiers in this war were defeated in a surprise attack the day after Christmas in the Battle of Trenton. For ten points, name this war in which Baron von Steuben drilled troops at Valley Forge, Pennsylvania, during the winter of 1777.",
      "answer": "American Revolutionary War"
    },
    {
      "question": "A three-part collection by this author depicts conditions in a besieged city in December, May, and August. The second part of an epilogue to a novel by this author attacks the Great Man theory of history, arguing that the importance of heroic figures like Napoleon is overrated. This author of Sevastopol Sketches wrote a novel about Pierre Bezuhkov set during the French invasion of Russia. For ten points, name this author of War and Peace.",
      "answer": "Leo Nikolayevich Tolstoy"
    },
    {
      "question": "Debate over this action was triggered by a plan to give Lorenzo Thomas a job. Prominent advocates for this action included John Bingham and an ailing Thaddeus Stevens. Edmund Ross earned a chapter of John F. Kennedy’s Profiles in Courage for casting the deciding vote against this action, which was a response to a violation of the Tenure of Office Act. The attempted firing of Edwin Stanton triggered, for ten points, what Congressional event that sought to remove Abraham Lincoln’s successor from office?",
      "answer": "impeaching Andrew Johnson"
    },
    {
      "question": "A symbol of authority possessed by the holder of this position was a set of nine cauldrons, or ding. A group of five legendary holders of this position are paired with the Three Sovereigns in many ancient texts, and the most prominent member of that group is usually named after the color yellow. The holder of this position was given the right and ability to rule from a divine provenance, which was called the Mandate of Heaven. For ten points, name this position held by monarchs from the Han Dynasty.",
      "answer": [
        "Emperor of China",
        "equivalents such as king of China",
        "ruler of China"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "One of these objects designed by Robert Moses was partially built using wartime rubble from England. Andrew Jackson vetoed a bill that would have created one of these structures named for Maysville, which would have been part of the Cumberland System. After his positive experience with the Autobahn, Dwight Eisenhower ordered the construction of, for ten points, what type of transportation infrastructure whose American examples include I-95 and Route 66?",
      "answer": [
        "roads",
        "specific answers, like highways",
        "turnpikes, etc.",
        "FDR Drive",
        "Maysville Road",
        "Cumberland Road",
        "Interstate system, Interstate Highway system, etc."
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Emmanuel de Roug´e coined the term for these people, who are depicted on the Medinet Habu temple. Fighting these people at the Battle of Djahy and the Battle of the Delta caused the depletion of Ramesses III’s treasury. The invasions of these people may have been caused by a famine in Anatolia, though they may also have been Philistines or Minoans fleeing a volcanic eruption. The Bronze Age Collapse was caused by, for ten points, what invaders of the New Kingdom of Egypt that came from the Mediterranean?",
      "answer": "Sea Peoples"
    },
    {
      "question": "This piece’s melody was also used for “When the Warrior Returns,” which celebrated Stephen Decatur’s victory in the Barbary Wars. The opening of this song is used to represent Lieutenant Pinkerton in Giacomo Puccini’s Madame Butterfly. The lyrics to this song were written aboard the HMS Tonnant and set to the tune of To Anacreon in Heaven. For ten points, name this patriotic song written during the defense of Fort McHenry by Francis Scott Key.",
      "answer": "The Star-Spangled Banner"
    },
    {
      "question": "To prepare for this battle, the winning commander designed a namesake “chequer” of yellow and black lines to better identify his ships. A tactic mirroring John Jervis’ maneuvers at Cape St. Vincent was employed at this battle to isolate the Bucentaure. The destruction of a Franco-Spanish navy at this battle ended Napoleon’s hopes of invading England. For ten points, name this 1805 victory for Lord Nelson, commemorated in a namesake London Square.",
      "answer": "Battle of Trafalgar"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man was nearly assassinated by the Italian anarchist Gennaro Rubino in 1902. This ruler attempted to abolish the military policy of Remplacement after his country’s neutrality was tenuously preserved in the Franco-Prussian War. This ruler earned the nickname the “Builder King” for his public works projects, including the Antwerpen-Centraal Railway Station. He commissioned Henry Stanley to lay claims to colonial territory in Africa; that territory later became the Congo Free State. For ten points, name this Belgian monarch.",
        "answer": "King Leopold II"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "While ruler of the Congo Free State, King Leopold II organized this mercenary army to extort the Congolese for ivory and rubber. Members of this group allegedly cut off the hands of workers who failed to reach their quotas.",
        "answer": [
          "Force Publique or the Public Force",
          "the Openbare Weermacht"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Iconic photos from this site include a snapshot of Zbigniew Brzezinski [z’big-nee-ev breh-ZHIN-skee] playing chess and Paul Vathis’ “Serious Steps” showing John F. Kennedy and Dwight Eisenhower walking side by side. This site’s Dogwood, Aspen and Laurel buildings have been used to house visitors like Anwar Sadat and Menachem Begin, who met on a 1979 retreat. For ten points, name this Presidential compound where Jimmy Carter helped broker a peace accord between Egypt and Israel.",
        "answer": "Camp David"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Camp David was Barack Obama’s hosting ground for the 38th G8 summit, where tensions escalated when Vladimir Putin sent this current Prime Minister of Russia to attend in his place.",
        "answer": "Dmitri Medvedev"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One composer from this present-day country used an extinct liturgical language for his Glagolitic Mass. Another composer from this country included a furiant in a suite inspired by Johannes Brahms’ Hungarian Dances and wrote his final symphony, partially inspired by Longfellow’s Song of Hiawatha, while he visited the USA. A symphonic poem about this country’s Vysehrad [vish-eh-rahd] castle premiered after its composer lost his hearing; that work opens a set of six pieces titled Ma Vlast. For ten points, name this modern-day country, the home of Leos Janacek [yahn-ah-check] and the composer of the Slavonic Dances and the New World Symphony, Antonin Dvorak [d’vor-zhak].",
        "answer": [
          "Czechia",
          "Czech Republic"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In addition to composers like Janacek and Dvorak, Czechia’s musical history includes this composer of the aforementioned Ma Vlast and The Bartered Bride.",
        "answer": "Bedrich Smetana"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This rebellion’s leader issued a manifesto criticizing the Green Springs monopoly on the beaver trade. This rebellion’s planners achieved success in an attack on the Susquehannock, but John Ingram was forced to take command after this rebellion’s leader died of dysentery. This rebellion was sparked by settlers who felt that the colonial government did not do enough to prevent attacks by natives. Jamestown was burned down as a result of, for ten points, what 1676 rebellion in Virginia?",
        "answer": "Bacon’s Rebellion"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Nathaniel Bacon may have been angry that he was not invited to join the trade circle of this Virginia governor, who returned to England after his poor handling of the rebellion.",
        "answer": "William Berkeley"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "These people “trampled on the bodies of saints [...] like dung in the streets,” according to Alcuin’s description of their raid on Lindisfarne. These people were recruited to form the Varangian Guard by the Byzantines. Charles the Simple signed the Treaty of Saint-Claire-sur-Epte, granting these people land in Western Europe, and they were granted Normandy after carrying out a series of raids down the Seine River in their longships. For ten points, name these seafaring marauders from Scandinavia who didn’t actually wear iconic two-horned caps.",
        "answer": "Vikings"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Vikings conquered England in 1016 under the leadership of this ruler. He defeated Edmund Ironside at Assandun to take power, and, like Alfred, is known as “the great.”",
        "answer": "Canute the Great or Cnut the Great"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This Chief Justice wrote that the power to determine whether a state government was a “legitimate republican” one was a political question in Luther v. Borden. This Chief Justice at the time of the Amistad case also wrote a controversial opinion denying the plaintiff standing on account of his race and ruling the Missouri Compromise unconstitutional. The Dred Scott v. Sanford case was decided by, for ten points, what Chief Justice who presided from 1836 to 1864?",
        "answer": "Roger Taney , but be lenient"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A Contract Clause case during Taney’s tenure concerned charters granted to construct these structures; that case was named after the “Charles River” and “Warren” examples of these structures.",
        "answer": [
          "bridges",
          "Charles River Bridge v. Warren Bridge"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This civilization’s writing system evolved into an “Epi” script, though their initial writings were recorded at the Cajascal [cah-has-kal] block in San Andres. This civilization became known as the “rubber people” for their ability to extract latex from nearby trees. Ritual bloodletting was practiced for the first time in Central America at this civilization’s center at San Lorenzo. For ten points, name this Mesoamerican civilization, known for their creation of large stone heads.",
        "answer": "Olmec civilization"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Olmec were the first to play this court-based Mesoamerican sport, which has had a modern resurgence. In later Mayan myth, the Hero Twins play this sport after descending to Xibalba [she-balba]",
        "answer": "Mesoamerican ball game"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This musician paid tribute to the head of the African National Congress in “Full Nelson.” The wife of Akhnaten lent her name to this man’s final all-acoustic album, Nefertiti, which featured Wayne Shorter and Herbie Hancock as part of his “second great quintet.” A 1957 compilation album by this man’s nonet lent its name to a genre that succeeded bebop. Birth of the Cool was performed by, for ten points, what jazz trumpeter who recorded Kind of Blue?",
        "answer": "Miles Davis"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The aforementioned track “Full Nelson” pays tribute to Nelson Mandela and appears on an album whose title pays tribute to this other South African human rights activist, the winner of the 1984 Nobel Peace Prize.",
        "answer": "Archbishop Desmond Mpilo Tutu"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Governors of New York",
      "prompt": "Name the governor of New York who...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Became President in 1933 and championed the New Deal.",
          "answer": [
            "Franklin Delano Roosevelt",
            "FDR"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was nicknamed “Old Kinderhook” and succeeded Andrew Jackson as President.",
          "answer": "Martin Van Buren"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was also the first Chief Justice of the Supreme Court.",
          "answer": "John Jay"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was a former Mafia prosecutor and unexpectedly lost a presidential election to Harry Truman.",
          "answer": "Thomas Dewey"
        },
        {
          "question": "Fathered the current governor, Andrew, and gave a keynote address at the 1984 DNC.",
          "answer": "Mario Cuomo"
        },
        {
          "question": "Became Vice President under Gerald Ford and led a wing of moderate Republicans.",
          "answer": "Nelson Aldrich Rockefeller"
        },
        {
          "question": "Inaugurated the Erie Canal and unsuccessfully challenged James Madison for the presidency.",
          "answer": "DeWitt Clinton"
        },
        {
          "question": "Defeated Rutherford B. Hayes in the popular vote, but not the Electoral College, in 1876.",
          "answer": "Samuel J. Tilden"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Black Death",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Disease whose bubonic variety caused the Black Death.",
          "answer": [
            "black",
            "bubonic plague"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Animals, other than humans, who spread the fleas that carried the disease.",
          "answer": "black rats"
        },
        {
          "question": "Religious group blamed for poisoning wells during the outbreaks, resulting in pogroms.",
          "answer": "Jewish people"
        },
        {
          "question": "Northern European country that was relatively unaffected by the disease, sparing cities like Krakow.",
          "answer": "Poland"
        },
        {
          "question": "Number of humors that medieval doctors believed in, influencing their treatment of victims.",
          "answer": "four humors"
        },
        {
          "question": "Type of mask worn by plague doctors that is now often worn in Carnival celebrations in Venice.",
          "answer": [
            "bird mask or beak mask",
            "anything indicating the mask includes a long, protruding nose"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "British monarch who won the Battle of Crecy and instituted the Statue of Laborers to deal with the depopulation caused by the Black Death.",
          "answer": "Edward III"
        },
        {
          "question": "Genoese colony on the Black Sea where the disease first entered Europe.",
          "answer": "Kaffa or Feodosia"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Incan Empire",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "European country whose conquistadors conquered the Inca.",
          "answer": "Spain"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country where those conquistadors then built cities like Lima.",
          "answer": "Peru"
        },
        {
          "question": "Conquistador who led the expedition against the Incan Empire.",
          "answer": "Francisco Pizarro"
        },
        {
          "question": "Final emperor of the Inca who defeated his brother Huascar in a civil war.",
          "answer": "Atahualpa"
        },
        {
          "question": "Two precious metals that filled three rooms in order to ransom that emperor.",
          "answer": [
            "gold and silver",
            "in either order"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Incan capital city, the site of the Sacsayhuaman [sak-say-wha-man] fortress.",
          "answer": "Cusco"
        },
        {
          "question": "Leader of the Neo-Inca state in Vilcabamba, or the 18th century rebel of the same name, or the 20th century rapper who adopted this name.",
          "answer": [
            "Tupac Amaru or Tupac Amaru II",
            "Tupac Amaru Shakur"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Language spoken throughout the empire that was suppressed under Spanish rule.",
          "answer": [
            "Quechua",
            "Runasimi"
          ]
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This scientist’s namesake constant is equal to the time derivative of the scale factor over the scale factor, and the reciprocal of that constant is equal to the age of the Universe. This man’s namesake (20 pts)",
        "law, which was discovered while working at the Mount Wilson Observatory, states that the recessional velocity of a galaxy is proportional to its distance from us; that implies the occurrence of the Big Bang. The “Pillars of Creation” (10 pts)",
        "photograph was taken by a device named for, for ten points, what American astronomer who names a space telescope launched in 1990?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Edwin Hubble",
        "Hubble constant, Hubble’s Law, and/or Hubble Space Telescope"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This speech laments how the “solitary inventor...has been overshadowed by scientists” and calls on Americans to avoid “plundering for our own ease and convenience...the precious resources of tomorrow.” This speech warns against allowing (20 pts)",
        "“public policy” to fall in the hands of the “scientific-technological elite” and warns against the “unwarranted influence” of the (10 pts)",
        "“military-industrial complex.” For ten points, name this speech, given three days before John F. Kennedy’s inaugural address, that ended a US President’s public career. ANSWER:DwightEisenhower’sFarewellAddress(acceptdescriptiveanswersofDwightEisenhower’s last speech as President) (3) A state named for this modern-day country existed for twenty-four hours under president Avgustyn Voloshyn. Symon Petliura led another state in this modern-day country, which was the site of an anti-Semitic nationalist movement led by Stepan (+) Bandera during World War II. Leonid Kuchma was overthrown as this country’s President in the 2004 (*) Orange Revolution, and this country was also the site of more recent Euromaidan protests. For ten points, name this country that lost control over the Crimean Peninsula after a 2014 Russian annexation."
      ],
      "answer": "Ukraine"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Secular and religious forces in this country clashed at the 1208 Battle of Vidines. Thorvald Konradsson brought missionaries to this country in the late 10th century. In 930 AD, the Law Rock marked the site in this country where the oldest (20 pts)",
        "parliament in the world was created; that body, the Althing, was twice led by Snorri Sturluson. In 1918, (10 pts)",
        "Denmark agreed to recognize a 25-year personal union with this country. For ten points, name this country where volcanic eruptions have affected air travel in Reykjavik [rek-ya-vik]."
      ],
      "answer": "Iceland"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 1968, a consolidation process in this state’s Duval County created what was briefly the largest city by land area in the US. The 2010 census recorded just 10 permanent residents in this state’s city of Lake Buena Vista, a small company town adjacent to (20 pts)",
        "Kissimmee. Pedro Men´dez de Avil´es founded the oldest continuously occupied European settlement in the US in 1565 in what is now this state. This state’s city of Titusville has suffered economically since the end of the (10 pts)",
        "Space Shuttle program. St. Augustine is in, for ten points, what southern US state whose largest by area is Jacksonville?"
      ],
      "answer": "Florida"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This country’s Liberal and Conservative parties agreed to trade off the presidency in a 16-year period called the National Front. The M-19 guerrilas became active in this country after Gustavo Rojas Pinilla lost a 1970 election. In 2016, this country’s president won the (20 pts)",
        "Nobel Peace Prize for brokering a peace deal that this country’s people rejected in a referendum. This country was the base of power of the Medellin (10 pts)",
        "Cartel, which ran the drug trade under Pablo Escobar. FARC rebels once fought in, for ten points, what country led by Juan Manuel Santos from Bogota?"
      ],
      "answer": "Colombia"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Charles Ruthenberg organized a parade in Cleveland to protest the jailing of this man. This man, one of the many co-founders of the Industrial Workers of the World, was defended by Clarence Darrow for his actions in the (20 pts)",
        "Pullman Strike. This man declared “when I rise it will be with the ranks, and not from the ranks” in a speech in (10 pts)",
        "Canton, Ohio protesting the World War I draft. For ten points, name this five-time Socialist presidential candidate who ran his last campaign in 1920 from a prison cell."
      ],
      "answer": "Eugene V. Debs"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This empire attempted to defuse ethnic tension in its west via the “Basic State Act,” equally recognized all languages. Unity within this empire was symbolized with the abbreviation k.u.k., indicating its (20 pts)",
        "“imperial and royal” nature. This empire was formed after Gyula Andrassy and Ferenc Deak negotiated a Compromise of 1867, and it was drawn into a (10 pts)",
        "war after assassins from the Black Hand killed Archduke Franz Ferdinand. For ten points, name this dual monarchy based in Vienna and Budapest that dissolved near the end of World War I."
      ],
      "answer": "Austria-Hungary"
    }
  ]
}